Hey, you know that smooth part of your
brain that's supposed to hold all your
knowledge of the causes and effects of
the French and Indian War? Well, I
reckon you're here to get that thing all
kinds of wrinkly, and I'm here to help.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milt, let's get to it. So, we are
now in a new time period, namely 1754 to
1800. And if you'll recall, tensions
between the colonies and big mama
Britain started heating up at the end of
the last period on account of several
things. But most important here was that
Great Britain went ahead and shut down
the colonist ability to migrate and
settle westward into the Ohio River
Valley. And chief among the reasons for
that prohibition was Britain's concern
that westward migration would create two
related problems. First, migration into
the Ohio River Valley would spark
conflict with the indigenous groups
living there. And it turns out the
British were right about this. As the
colonists thumbmed their noses at the
British prohibition and moved westward
anyway, they encountered stiff
resistance from an indigenous alliance
led by the Shaune and the Delawarees.
And then the second problem the British
feared was a conflict with the French
who happened to claim all that land for
their own self. And as it turns out, Big
Mama Britain was right to fear such a
thing because, well, you know, it ended
up sparking a whole dang war as more and
more colonists moved into the area. And
as it turns out, the inciting incident
for this war was committed in 1753 by
none other than our boy George
Washington. So Washington was appointed
Lieutenant Colonel of the Virginia
militia and sent to confront the French
about encroaching on British territory
in the Ohio River Valley. Long story
short, the French commander at Fort
Dukane ignored Washington's warning.
>> Washington, do you not have a cherry
tree to chop down somewhere?
And then Washington, being no fan of a
proper French snub, returned several
months later with his own men and their
American Indian allies and attacked the
French. Anyway, in the end, Washington
and his men got hammered by the French
and had to retreat. Regardless, this
skirmish marked the beginning of the
French and Indian War. Now, if you know
your European history, Britain and
France were at war like every other
weekend. But this one was unique in that
it started in North America and then
spread somewhat worldwide into a larger
conflict that became known as the Seven
Years War. But anyway, once the war
broke out, Britain understood pretty
quickly that to have any shot of
protecting themselves against French
encroachment, they needed a powerful
alliance with American Indians. And to
that end, the British called the Albany
Congress, whose chief purpose was to
forge an alliance with the Irakcoy
Confederacy. And while the Irakcoy
initially wanted to remain neutral in
order to keep trading prospects open
with both the French and the British,
eventually they did end up supporting
the British in the conflict. And
meanwhile, the French secured alliances
with the Alangquin and Hiron peoples.
Anyway, something important happened at
the Albany Congress that you're going to
need to remember. Our boy Benjamin
Franklin proposed the Albany plan of
union which would create a council made
up of delegates from all the colonies.
They would have the power to tax and
raise militias for the common defense
and create lasting strategic relations
with American Indians. And while this
effort marked the most significant first
attempt to unite the colonies under a
single representative body, the plan
failed miserably. And that's because
colonial leaders thought that the plan
took away too much of their power to
govern themselves independently. But
then on the other side of the ocean,
Great Britain poo pooed the plan because
they felt like it took away too much of
their authority over the colonies. So
sorry, Ben. No colonial union for you.
And hey, before I tell you about who won
the war and all the effects it had, let
me tell you that you might want to check
out my A pushheimler review guide if you
want to get an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May. It has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible, like exclusive unit review
videos that you're not going to see here
on YouTube, note guides to follow along,
practice multiple choice questions for
each unit, full length practice exams,
and answer keys for every dang bit of
it. So, if that's the kind of help you
need, then get that clicky finger out
and check the link in the description.
Okay, so here's where I tell you that
even though over the course of the war
the French seemed to be mopping the
floor with the British, the British
actually ended up winning the war. And
one of the main reasons for the British
victory was that the British colonists
way outnumbered the French in North
America. I mean, that's what I've been
telling you since unit one. The British
colonists were multiplying like mad. And
by the time the war broke out, they
outnumbered the French by a factor of
10. That's a lot of colonists, Steve. It
sure is. And that advantage led to a
British victory in the signing of the
Peace of Paris in 1763. Now, that peace
treaty fundamentally changed the map of
North America, and that's going to have
some serious consequences. So, Spain
seated Florida to Great Britain in order
to get their hands back on Cuba and the
Philippines, which again signals the
global nature of this war. And then
France seated their territory west of
the Mississippi River to Spain. And then
the biggest deal of all, France gave up
their territory in the Ohio River Valley
to Great Britain. And oh, what a time to
rejoice for the British colonists. Like,
that's all they ever wanted was to
migrate into this area and get their
agriculture on. And baby, that's exactly
what they did. And everybody was happy.
But here comes Big Mama Britain to shut
down the migration party quick, fast,
and in a hurry. You see, even though
these lands were now altogether French
list, they were still home to a
fantastic array of American Indian
groups who, to put it mildly, were not
too excited to see this flood of
colonists gobbling up their territory.
And by American Indian reckoning, the
British were definitely worse than the
French, since the French honored local
giftgiving traditions and didn't create
large settlements. But the British were
opposite on both counts. And so in
response to this fresh wave of
migration, an indigenous leader named
Pontiac assembled an alliance of Ottawa,
Padawati, and Huron leaders to resist
British encroachment. They went ahead
and launched attacks against British
settlements. And as news of the attack
spread through the colonies, British
colonists retaliated. This got Britain
real cranky because the colonists were
fighting with American Indians as a
whole without distinguishing which one
was an ally and which one was a foe. And
so since Big Mama was real tired and
real broke from fighting the Seven Years
War, she really didn't want to devote
more resources to putting down the
conflicts erupting in the Ohio River
Valley. So Parliament issued the
Proclamation of 1763, which forbade
British colonists from migrating west
beyond the Appalachian Mountains. And
the colonists, who put it mildly, were
uh not fans of this move. I mean, in
their minds, the whole stinking point of
the war that they themselves had fought
was to gain possession of this land so
that they could migrate west. And now
here's this law saying that they have to
keep their hind parts in the east
because Britain isn't willing to do the
work that it takes to open the
opportunities for migration. So yeah,
this got the colonist all kinds of
resentful with respect to their imperial
overlords across the sea. But from Great
Britain's perspective, it was a
different story altogether. I mean, yes,
they had won the war against France and
gained all this territory, but it cost a
fortune to do so. In fact, during the
course of the war, Great Britain's
national debt doubled, and that meant
that they were in a precarious situation
economically. And then to further add to
their economic troubles, the crazy
population growth in the colonies and
the constant border conflicts with
American Indians meant that the cost of
running the colonies had increased
fivefold. So it made all the sense in
the world from their perspective to
restrain the westward migration of the
colonist if only to take a minute to
recover economically. But then something
else started making sense to Great
Britain. What I mean is since the
colonists were reaping some of the
rewards of the victory, it made sense
that they would help pay for the war
that gave them those rewards. Mama was
like, "Hey, I'll buy you the car, but
you better get a job because you're
going to have to pay for the gas and
insurance." And so, in order to make the
colonist foot their part of the war
bill, Parliament passed a number of new
taxation and trade laws that would force
the colonies to serve the economy of
Great Britain. That's going to cause
more than a little tension, but that
juicy story is for the next video. Okay,
you can click here to keep watching my
other unit 3 videos, or you can click
here to grab my A Push Himler review
guide, which has everything you need to
study as fast as possible. I appreciate
you stopping by, and I'll catch you on
the flip-flop. Himler out.